NYSUT President's Office Files. 6174/001
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
NYSUT President's Office Files
1831- 1999
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
New York State United Teachers (NYSUT)
Hobart, Thomas Y. Jr.
Ianuzzi, Richard
6174/001
100.56 cubic feet
99 linear ft.
Articles, reports, pamphlets, correspondence.
5830496
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, January 22, 2013
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, November 03, 2014
Biographical / Historical
New York State United Teachers (NYSUT) was created in 1972 by the merger of the New York State Teachers Association (NYSTA) and the United Teachers of New York (UTNY). NYSTA had been affiliated with the National Education Association (NEA), and UTNY with the American Federation of Teachers (AFT). UTNY was the statewide organization whose United Federation of Teachers (UFT), led by Albert Shanker, was the predominant teachers' union in New York City. In joining with United Teachers and affiliating with the AFT, NYSUT also became a member union of the AFL-CIO.
In 1976, NYSUT voted to disaffiliate with the NEA. Some locals left NYSUT and created the NYEA (New York Educators Association), which became the state affiliate for the NEA. In the early 1980s, NYEA changed its name to NEA-NY.
NYEA/NEA- NY viewed association with the AFL-CIO's industrial unions as undermining the professional image and independence of teachers. The two organizations also differed strongly on aspects of the governance structure, particularly with respect to ethnic minority representation, with NYSUT opposed to mandatory minimums. The rivalry between NYSUT and NYEA/NEA-NY in organizing new locals expended a great deal of resources for both labor organizations.
While competition with NYEA/NEA-NY was a constant focus of NYSUT's organizing efforts for teachers, NYSUT was also organizing college faculty members, nurses, and other non-teaching personnel. Once members were organized, NYSUT continued to advocate for teachers' and other workers' rights through contract support and legal services at the local level and political involvement at the state and federal levels, supporting candidates and legislation that protected funding, due process, and working conditions.
NEA-N Y merged with NYSUT in 2006, by which time NYSUT had grown to more than half a million members, becoming the largest union in New York State.
Biographical / Historical
Thomas Y. Hobart, Jr., served as president of NYSUT since it was created in 1973 from the merger of NYSTA (New York State Teacher's Association, founded in 1845 and the largest state affiliate of the National Education Association) and UTNY (United Teachers of New York, affiliated with American Federation of Teachers-AFL-CIO). Hobart was a prime mover in the disaffiliation of NYSUT from the NEA, and reaffirmation of affiliation with the AFT, in 1976. He was involved in jurisdictional disputes that followed the split for many years, as NYSUT and NEA (through its affiliate, New York Educators Association) fought for membership at the local level; the rivalry was finally resolved when the two again merged in 2006, still maintaining strong ties with the AFT.
The president serves as a vice president of the AFT and vice president of New York State AFL-CIO and represents NYSUT in high-level interactions with state elected and appointed officials, particularly the Department of Education; international labor organizations; political parties; nonprofit service organizations such as the New York Special Olympics; and other unions. The president or his assistant has often visited regional offices to maintain firsthand contact with local concerns.
Hobart retired in 2005 and was succeeded by NYSUT's current president, Richard Ianuzzi.
Scope and Contents
Covers the period roughly corresponding to Tom Hobart's presidency, 1982-2004, with some files from the 1970s and a few as early as 1831. Documents Hobart's activities on the NYSUT Board of Directors, Executive Committee, Administrative Committee, officers' meetings, NY Special Olympics Board of Directors, international trips, and correspondence.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 6174/001 P: NYSUT President's Office Photographs. All other 6174 collections
Arrangement
Series Presidents Files: NYSUT Subseries
Series Presidents files: Subseries 2
Teachers' unions -- New York (State); Hobart, Thomas Y. Jr.; Ianuzzi, Richard; New York State United Teachers. Archives; AFL-CIO. Archives; AFL-CIO, Executive Council. Archives; American Federation of Teachers. Archives; American Federation of Teachers, Executive Council. Archives; Advisory Committee to the Permanent Interagency on Early Childhood Programs. Archives; Aspen Institute. Archives; International Federation of Free Teachers' Unions. Archives; Martin Luther King Commission. Archives; Public Employee Safety and Health Bureau. Archives
5830496
- AFL-CIO Executive Council Meetings Receipts and Expenses, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Related materials
- AFL-CIO National Convention (NYC) (folder 1 of 3), 1995 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  October 23-26, 1995. Campaign materials for Tom Donahue and Barbara Easterling; AFL-CIO News, October 23-26
- AFL-CIO National Convention (folder 2 of 3), 1995 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Campaign materials for John Sweeney; tentative program; newspaper clippings
- AFL-CIO National Convention (folder 3 of 3), 1995 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Resolutions; constitution; Executive Council report; text of keynote address by President Donahue; delegate badges; related materials
- AFL-CIO National Convention (Detroit, MI), 1991 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Official convention call; agenda; list of resolutions from NYS AFL-CIO; printed booklet, "Health Care Bargaining: A Guide for the Nineties"; resource catalog of video, audio, print, advertising and promotional materials from the Labor Institute for Public Affairs, AFL-CIO, fall 1991; AFL-CIO News, November 13, 1991
- AFL-CIO Regional Conferences (NYC), 1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  4/10-4/11/87. Notice of health care seminar on June 29, 1987; list of regional conference dates and cities
- AFL-CIO Winter Meetings (Bal Harbour, FL), 1991 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  2/13-2/22/91. Meeting notice; agenda for February 1990 meeting; draft of speech re pension system
- AFT (American Federation of Teachers), 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  "Classrooms Held Hostage: Restoring Order to Our Schools," American Federation of Teachers President Albert Shanker's Address to the 1995 AFT Conference on Discipline and Safety; AFT Convention Resolutions, adopted July 1994; Report: AFT Defense Committee, Prepared for the AFT Executive Council Meeting, July 27, 1995; report of the AFT College-School Task Force on Student Achievement; "Closing the Circle: Making Higher Education a Full Partner in Systemic Reforms"; fact sheets, "First Things First: What Americans Expect from Public Schools - Summary" and "A Bill of Rights and Responsibilities for Learning: Standards for Conduct, Standards for Achievement"; ad tear sheet by AFL-CIO re immigration; booklet, "Helping Your Child Learn Math," co-published by the AFT and the U.S. Department of Education, targeting union members
- AFT Convention (Anaheim, CA) (folder 1 of 2), 1994 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  July 15-20, 1994. Approved budget for fiscal year 1994-95; lists of committee members; 1992-94 Report of the Officers of the AFT; daily summaries; "Key Findings from a Nationwide Survey of AFT Teacher Members," Peter D. Hart Research Associates
- AFT Convention (folder 2 of 2), 1994 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Program; roll call of delegates; daily summary, featuring Vice President Al Gore, July 17; 1994 Committee Report on Resolutions; 1994 Constitutional Amendments Committee Report and Special Orders of Business; 12-K Divisional Meeting and Agenda; convention recap; Progressive Caucus agenda
- AFT Convention (Pittsburgh, PA), 1992 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  August 11-16, 1992. Proposed convention resolutions; roll call of delegates; 1990-92 Report of Officers; talking points for media interviews; constitution as of July 1990; committee reports; guide to black children's books; printed daily summaries of proceedings
- AFT Convention: Executive Committee, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  August 11-16, 1992. Agenda; special order of business: endorsement of Bill Clinton and Al Gore for President and Vice President; report of opinion survey by Peter D. Hart Research Associates re presidential candidate preference of teachers, July 25-27, 1992; proposed constitutional amendments; resolution re national standards and assessments
- AFT Convention: Executive Council, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  August 11-16, 1992. Agenda; newsletter, "On the Hill: AFT Rates the 102nd Congress"; background paper on national standards and assessments; draft position paper, "U.S. Education - The Task Before Us"
- AFT Convention, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Report
- AFT Convention, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  August 19-23, 1974. Proceedings
- AFT Executive Committee Meeting (Bal Harbour, FL), 1996 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  February 13, 1996. Agenda; budgets; list of contributions to political candidates; resumes of new hires; statistics re public school enrollment, child poverty; article re privatization of public schools, by Max B. Sawicky; newspaper clippings
- AFT Executive Committee Meeting (Hershey, PA), 1991 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  October 21, 1991. AFT constitution as of July 1990; agenda
- AFT Executive Committee Meeting (Washington, D.C.), 1991 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  July 15, 1991. Agenda; budgets for organizational assistance programs, FY 1990-91; joint statement by AAUP, NEA, and AFT on the financial crisis in higher education, June 12; excerpts from Tentative Agreement between the Cincinnati Board of Education and Cincinnati Federation of Teachers, June 28; contract highlights; Interim Agreement between Wisconsin Education Association Council and the Wisconsin Federation of Teachers; legal ruling by the Ohio State Employment Relations Board, "Impasse Findings and Report," Toledo City Schools and Toledo Federation of Teachers, March 19, 1991; "Colleagues Still," statement on elimination of mandatory retirement, by John M. Reilly, president, United University Professors, Local 2190, Advisory Commission on Higher Education of the AFT (Study Group on Retirement); cover letter to Hobart from St. Louis Teachers Union urging endorsement of proposed AFT 1992 Convention resolution, with supporting materials (condensed paper by Henry George, "Progress and Poverty"; editorials and newspaper interviews with union leaders endorsing two-rate property tax)
- AFT Executive Committee (Bal Harbour, FL), 1991 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  February 12, 1991. Agenda; AFT financial report, December 31, 1990; affiliation agreement between Dearborn School Employees Independent Union and Michigan Federation of Teachers; list of organizational assistance program allocations, February 13-14, 1991; list of campaign contributions for the 1990 election cycle by COPE Department, motion to approve contributions for 1990/1992; AFT newsletter, On the Hill, January/February 1991, re nationwide election results
- AFT Executive Committee (Washington, D.C.), 1990 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  September 25, 1990. Agenda; minutes re financial allocations; FNHP Report to the AFT Executive Council re Health Care Division organizing and collective bargaining activities
- AFT Executive Committee (Boston), 1990 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  July 5, 1990. Agenda; AFT financial report and budget proposal, April 30, 1990; list of organizational assistance program allocations
- AFT Executive Committee (Washington, D.C.), 1990 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  April 23, 1990. Agenda; list of contribution requests and allocations
- AFT Executive Council -- Special Meeting (NYC), 1996 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  June 24, 1996. Proposed Jurisdictional Agreement between the National Education Association and the American Federation of Teachers, AFL-CIO; memo re no-raid agreement; handwritten notes
- AFT Executive Council Meeting (Washington, D.C.), 1995 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  July 27, 1995. Agenda; Art Department Reports; 1994-95 budget for organizational assistance programs
- AFT Executive Council Meeting (Hershey, PA), 1991 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  10/22-10/23/91. Minutes of meeting; financial statements, June 20, 1991 and 1990; Executive Council Survey Results; AFT Proposals to AFT Staff Union, September 30; confidential "no-raid" agreement between Florida Education Association/United and FTP-NEA, October 7; list of contribution requests and allocations by Executive Committee at October 21 meeting
- AFT Executive Council Meeting (Washington, D.C.), 1991 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  July 16-17, 1991. Minutes of meeting; department reports; Defense Committee report; Technology Committee report; report of investigation of election in Wappingers Federation of Transit, Custodial and Maintenance Workers, Local 3745; AFT Constitution, correct as of July 1990
- AFT Executive Council February (Bal Harbour, FL), 1991 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  13-14, 1991. Minutes of meeting; memo re AFT local and national activities re Persian Gulf war, January 25; International Affairs Department report; AFT Constitution, correct as of July 1990; letter from AFT president Albert Shanker to Roger Porter, assistant to the president for economic and domestic policy, following up on conversation on development of national examinations, August 15, 1990, with attached proposal to president's Education Advisory Committee and April 1985 article in Education Researcher, "Standards, Curriculum, and Performance: A Historical and Comparative Perspective," by Daniel and Lauren Resnick
- AFT Executive Council (Washington, D.C.), 1990 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  September 26-27, 1990. Agenda and minutes of September 26 meeting; letter from Executive Board of Kansas City, Missouri, Federation of Teachers, Local 691, asking for investigation of president of Missouri Federation, September 10; Defense Committee report re defense of teachers facing discipline for drug possession, tenure denials, etc; legislative report; proposed resolution, 1990 United Nations World Summit for Children, with attached description of AFT's involvement in summit; list of locals to be reinstated; list of committee memberships
- AFT Executive Council (Boston), 1990 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  July 5, 1990. Agenda; financial report and budget proposal, April 30, 1990; list of AFT defense cases on behalf of teachers facing discipline for psychiatric problems, etc; newsletter, Chicago Union Teacher, July 1990
- AFT Executive Council and Committee (Washington, D.C.), 1990 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  April 23-25, 1990. Agenda; minutes; list of defense cases on behalf of teachers facing discipline for falsifying test results, sexual misconduct, etc.; proposed resolutions on wide range of issues; opinion articles re inappropriateness of commercial advertising in classroom; materials re governor's races, including questionnaire for candidates
- AFT Executive Council (Florida), 1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  February 14-16, 1989. Agenda; minutes; financial report, December 31, 1989; forecasted budget proposal, July 1, 1989 - June 30, 1992; membership count, January 1990; defense cases; resolutions; policy essay, "Milestone of Tombstone: The Wagner Act at 50," Harvard Journal on Legislation, winter 1986
- AFT School-to-Work Transition Task Force, see School-to-Work
- AFT State Federation Presidents Conference (Scottsdale, AZ), 1990 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Program for conference, November 13-17; list of participants; outline of discussion of AFT Futures Committee; ideas for small group discussion; Citizen Action supplemental material for "Universal Health Care: The Only Applicable Solution to the Health Care Crisis," November 15; AFT booklet/poster, "It's Up to You: Building a Safer Approach to Universal Hygiene," with instructions for teachers for preventing HIV and other infectious transmission; NEA booklet, "Guidelines for the Delineation of Roles and Responsibilities for the Safe Delivery of Specialized Health Care in the Educational Setting," May 1, 1990; correspondence
- AFT State Federations, Advisory Council on, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  August 29-30, 1995. Memo from Hobart re first meeting agenda; program for 1994 State Federation Conference
- AFT Trip to Germany, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Correspondence and related materials in German re conference in Frankfurt, March 7-11; Hobart's travel journal; IFFTU (International Federation of Free Trade Unions) newsletter, Workers in Education, including article re new Germany, January 1991; newspaper clippings; handwritten notes
- AFT Quest, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  July 27-30, 1995. Sheraton Washington Hotel, Washington. AFT Quest '95 program, "Higher Stakes, Higher Standards: Designing Schools Where Children Achieve"; guide to technology, guide to exhibits; memo re media interviews at Quest, with attached sheet of talking point re privatization
- AFT/NYSUT Meeting, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  June 28, 1995. Copies of memo to Hobart requesting suggestions for whom to invite to meeting, and topics, with handwritten names; handwritten note re topics
- Advisory Committee to the Permanent Interagency Committee on Early Childhood Programs, New York State, see Early Childhood Programs
- Affiliation Requests, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Memos, collective bargaining agreements, and letters of acceptance re requests for NYSUT affiliation from Depew Transportation Employees Association (Western New York Regional Office), January 28, 1992; Organization of Certified Teaching Assistants and Registered Professional School Nurses: Union Endicott Central School District, March 6, 1992; Office Staff Association of South Huntington, March 13, 1992; Northport-East Northport Teacher-Aide Association, March 25, 1992; School Bus Drivers Unit Association of Cattaraugus, May 6, 1992; Watervliet Support Staff Association, June 23, 1992; Union Endicott Maintenance Workers Association, July 8, 1992; Massena Federation of Summer School Teachers, July 9, 1992; Dansville Support Staff Association, August 10, 1992; Lyons Support Staff Association, September 15, 1992; Union of Middletown School Employees, November 3, 1992 and September 13, 1993; Border City (Geneva, NY) Teachers Association, November 12, 1992; Faculty Association of Jamestown Community College, November 24, 1992; Worchester Central School Non-Teaching Personnel, March 3, 1993; Mt. Pleasant School Related Employees, March 3, 1993; Schalmont Teachers Association, March 3, 1993; Rocky Point School Related Personnel Association, May 27, 1993; Rockland Community College Federation of Administrators, May 28, 1993; Southern Tier Substitute Teachers, November 29, 1993
- Affiliation Requests, 1989-1991 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Memos, collective bargaining agreements, status sheets, and letters of acceptance re requests for NYSUT affiliation from Freeport Teachers Aides and Assistants Association, April 12, 1989; Union-Endicott Cafeteria Assn., Union-Endicott Aides Assn., Library Support Personnel Assn., May 4, 1989; Germantown T.A., May 19, 1989; Substitutes United in Broome, September 11, 1989; Schoharie Central Employees Association, October 31, 1989; Spencerport Aides Association, November 28, 1989; Secondary Teaching Assistants (Huntington, L.I.; Suffolk Regional Office), December 1, 1989; Edmeston Central School Faculty Association, January 17, 1990; Orchard Park Central School Educational Support Staff Association, March 29, 1990; Harpursville Support Staff Assn., June 28, 1990; BOCES United Employees 06-220, November 17, 1990; Madison Central School Teachers Association, February 6, 1991; Canton School Secretarial Association, December 3, 1990; Ulster County BOCES T.O, March 12, 1991; Berne-Knox-Westerlo Support Staff Association, June 10, 1991; York Teachers Association, June 27, 1991; Babylon TA (constitution), September 12, 1991; School Alliance for Substitutes in Education, November 18, 1991; Carthage Central Non-Teaching Association, November 18, 1991; CEWW BOCES (Plattsburgh Regional Office), November 27, 1991; Cobbelskill TA, December 5, 1991
- Agency Fee, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Memos re Supreme Court decision re collection of a fee by a union from a nonmember
- AIDS, 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Informational brochures on AIDS; memo to AFT Executive Council from general counsel re policies adopted by Georgia and Florida requiring testing of teachers and students "suspected" of having been exposed, June 30, 1987, with attached state board resolutions; NYSUT memos re whether school districts can impose mandatory testing, 1985; draft NYSUT position paper on AIDS, April 14, 1986, with attached recommendations by U.S. Department of Health and Human Services and Centers for Disease Control; guidelines by NYS Department of Health for education of infected children, September 4, 1985; press release by NYS Education Department re admission to school of children with AIDS, September 4, 1985; AFT proposed policy statement, 10/29/85, with proposed changes; NEA guidelines for dealing with AIDS in schools, October 9, 1985; editorial from Wall Street Journal calling for routine testing, May 26, 1987; related newspaper clippings
- Amalgamated Bank, 1982-1987 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  Statement of Condition 1987; New York magazine article, April 5, 1982
- Apartheid, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  Statement by the NYS Office of the State Comptroller re the New York State Retirement Fund and South Africa, September 1l; report, "South Africa: Is Peaceful Change Possible?" by Bayard Rustin, Charles Bloomstein, Walter Naegle; newspaper clippings, including New York Times op-ed by Desmond Tutu re sanctions
- Ashe, Bernard, 1992-1994 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  "The Taylor Law Scope of Bargaining," response of Bernard F. Ashe, general counsel, NYSUT, May 7, 1992; New York Law Journal clipping re Ashe as highest-ranking black in the American Bar Association, August 9, 1993; related clippings
- Aspen Institute, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  Correspondence re seminar programs; brochures; newsletter
- Aspen Institute, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  Aspen Institute Quarterly, 1990; brochures; program calendar; correspondence
- Aspen Institute, 1982-1987 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  Executive Program brochure, 1987; conference report, "United States-Soviet Relations: Building a Congressional Cadre," August 12-16, 1987; newsletters, Aspen Institute Chronicle, 1987; lists of alumni, 1986; executive program reading lists for Justice and Society Seminar, 1982; American Experience Seminar; Tradition and Change Seminar
- Aspen Institute: Celebration on the Contributions of Mortimer Adler, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  August 19-21, 1994. Correspondence re event honoring moderator of institute; list of presenters; typed highly abbreviated notes
- Aspen Institute: Wye Seminar, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  6/10-6/12/88. List of participants and agenda; brochures; newsletter, "Aspen Institute Chronicle"; report, "The Americas in 1988: A Time for Choices: A Report of the Inter-American Dialogue"; newspaper by Roosevelt Center for American Policy Studies, "The Presidential Candidates' Views on Central America U.S. Trade Policy"; handwritten notes
- Aspen Institute: Wye Seminar, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  12/5-12/7/86. Brochure, "Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies"; brochure for Executive Seminars, 1987; brochure for Wye Woods conference center, Maryland; program calendar; handwritten notes
- Aspen Institute: Wye Seminar, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 23)